Finding Aid for Aberbach-Walker Detroit Riot Studies records, 1967-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Aberbach-Walker Detroit Riot Studies records 1967-1971
University of Michigan. Institute of Public Policy Studies.
24 linear feet
87200 Bimu C448 2
Records, 1967-1971, of the studies on the Detroit riot of 1967 conducted by Joel Aberbach and Jack Walker, staff members of the Institute of Public Policy Studies of the University of Michigan. Includes survey forms (1967, 1968 and 1971) and audio-tapes of interviews with Detroit civic leaders and administrative records of the project.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were placed in the library by Professor Joel Aberbach (donor no. 7275 ) in 1985.
The records are closed to research without written permission of either Joel Aberbach or Jack L. Walker.
Immediately after the 1967 Detroit riots, professors Joel Aberbach and Jack L. Walker conceived of a study to examine the attitudes of individuals throughout metropolitan Detroit. Financed by federal funds channeled through the Institute for Public Policy Studies, they established a team of interviewers who began to talk to a carefully selected sample population in September 1967. Follow up studies were conducted in 1968 and 1971. In addition to the sample population, interviews were conducted with a number of civic leaders in 1968. The findings of these surveys have been published in summary form, as well as in Aberbach's and Walker's jointly authored Race in the City: political trust and public policy in the new urban system (Boston: Little, Brown, 1973).
Measuring 24 linear feet, the records are divided into three series, one for each "wave" of interviews. The 1967 Survey Forms (13 linear feet) consists solely of completed survey forms. Each form is approximately 40 pages in length and asked respondents to answer a wide variety of searching questions. Information is regularly recorded on survey scales, but interviewers frequently augmented this information through annotations on the form.
The 1968 Survey material (3 linear feet) consists primarily of completed 1968 survey forms, which were about 30 pages each in length and similar in content to the 1967 instrument. In addition there are interviews with civic leaders that consist of both a survey form and a tape recording of the interview.
The 1971 Survey material (8 linear feet) consists primarily of survey forms that are very similar to those used in 1968.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.)--History--20th century.; Municipal government--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Race relations.; Riots--Michigan--Detroit--History--20th century.
Contributors:
Aberbach, Joel D.; Walker, Jack L.
- 1967 Survey Forms
  - 1000-1069 (Box 1)
  - 1070-1135 (Box 2)
  - 1136-1199 (Box 3)
  - 1200-1216 (Box 4)
  - 2001-2049 (Box 4)
  - 2050-2115 (Box 5)
  - 2116-2195 (Box 6)
  - 2196-2227 (Box 7)
  - 3001-3023 (Box 7)
  - 3024-3033 (Box 8)
  - 4001-4052 (Box 8)
  - 4053-4067 (Box 9)
  - 5001-5050 (Box 9)
  - 5051-5095 (Box 10)
  - 6001-6017 (Box 10)
  - 6018-6085 (Box 11)
  - 6086-6149 (Box 12)
  - 6150-6219 (Box 13)
  - 6220-6222 (Box 14)
- 1968 Survey
  - Second Wave Non-Interviews (Box 14)
  - Respondent List (Box 14)
  - Survey Forms
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - 1001-1214 (Box 14)
    - 2001-2119 (Box 14)
    - 2119-6212 (Box 15)
      (many gaps)
  - Detroit Bureaucrats 1967
    - General, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Planning (Box 16)
      (interviews 10-19)
    - Community Relations/Civil Service (Box 16)
      (interviews 21-29)
    - Housing (Box 16)
      (interviews 30-39)
    - MCHRD and Poverty (Box 16)
      (interviews 40-49)
    - Health (Box 16)
      (interviews 51-59)
    - Fire/Parks and Recreation (Box 16)
      (interviews 61-69)
    - State Commissions regarding Community Development, Community Renewal, and Children and Youth (Box 16)
      (interviews 71-79)
    - Budget Bureau/Corporation Council (Box 16)
      (interviews 81-89)
    - Department of Public Works/Detroit Street Railways/Civil Defense (Box 16)
      (interviews 91-99)
    - Police (Box 16)
  - Code Sheets -- Detroit Administration (Box 16)
  - Detroit Administration Codebook
    - Corrected (Box 16)
    - General (Box 16)
  - New Detroit Committee
    - General (Box 16)
    - Codebook (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Index Cards (Box 16)
  - Tape Recordings of interviews with Detroit Bureaucrats (Box 16)
    (number on tape corresponds to interview number on folder)
- 1971 Survey
  - Panel Information (names and addresses) 1-3038 (Box 17)
  - Survey Forms
    - 1-110 (Box 17)
    - 111-320 (Box 18)
    - 321-480 (Box 19)
    - 481-620 (Box 20)
    - 621-780 (Box 21)
    - 781-874 (Box 22)
    - x301-x750 (Box 22)
    - X751-x4043 (Box 23)
    - Other (Box 23)
  - 4x6 Card Index
  - Coding Sheets (Box 24)